A Guide to the Moulse-Huff Genealogical Collection 1970s-1990s
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
A Guide to the Moulse-Huff Genealogical Collection
Roanoke Public Libraries
2012.1.06
5 record storage boxes and 2 drop-front, flat storage boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Connie Mattox
Biographical Note
Helen Huff Moulse (1910-1997) was a lifelong resident of Salem, Virginia. She married fellow Salem resident George Hampton “Hamp” Moulse in 1933 and raised two children. In the 1970s she began researching her family history. In 1981 she completed paperwork tracing part of the Huff lineage to Revolutionary War soldier John Huff and became a member of Daughters of the American Revolution. She continued to research her genealogy until the 1990s, compiling the letters, charts, and documents that form this collection. She belonged to Ridgewood Baptist Church in Salem for many years. The Moulse family has lived in Southwestern Virginia for many generations. The Moulse, Mowles, Aliff, Adams and Mattox families are all well-represented in this collection. There is also material about the Oklahoma branch of the Mowles family. Moulse/Mowles family reunions were held in Mowles Spring Park in Salem, VA starting in 1979. The Huff family has also inhabited Southwestern Virginia for many generations. John Huff, Sr. originally lived in Pennsylvania, but later settled in Virginia after participating in the American Revolution. The family married into the Cannaday, Early, and Richardson families.
Scope and Content
The Moulse Huff Genealogy Collection consists of seven boxes of documents – five record boxes and two oversize boxes – stored in the Special Collections in Virginia Room. Materials contained within the collection include handwritten notes and correspondence, photocopies of original records such as marriage and death certificates, snapshot and portrait photographs in black and white, color, negative, and photocopy form, memorial booklets from funerals and brochures about local places, photocopied excerpts from published books, and numerous newspaper clippings, including obituaries, marriage announcements, and articles featuring relatives. Much of the collection is pedigree charts, family trees, and family group sheets that list married couples and their offspring. Oversize materials include copies of records and very large hand-drawn Moulse family tree charts. There is also a large scrapbook featuring Moulse family history and family reunions. Also, two tintype photographs There are photocopies of document such as will and marriage licenses dating back to the early 1800s, but the earliest original documents are photographs from about 1890. There are also original marriage, will, and death records and a few pieces of correspondence from the 1930s. The bulk of the collection consists of photocopies of historic material, original notes and correspondence, color snapshots and portrait photographs, and genealogist’s family group sheets and pedigree charts created in the 1980s and 1990s. Folder titles are chosen to describe the bulk of the folder’s contents, not every name included. Although the collection is nominally organized by last name, information about surnames is actually found throughout the collection. Information about the Huff family is not found exclusively in folders labeled Huff, but may also be found in Moulse, Cannaday, and other names. Only about half of the photographs in the collection are identified. The Moulse, Mowles, Aliff, Adams and Mattox families are all well-represented in this collection. Most documents such as marriage licenses, armed service records and wills are photocopies of original records, but there are original documents for G. Hampton Moulse and some of his siblings. This collection includes invitations and informal photographs from the reunions. The Huff family married into the Cannaday, Early, and Richardson families. Most documents such as marriage licenses, armed service records and wills are photocopies of original records, but there are early photographs of the Huff and Richardson families.
Arrangement
Documents are arranged in groupings by last name, with oversize documents stored separately. A few non-name documents grouped by location.
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Moulse-Mowles: Coat of Arms, heraldry, photo and certificates undated (Folder 1)
  - Moulse-Huff: Coat of Arms, heraldry and business correspondence undated (Folder 2)
  - Mowles-Moulse: family reunion announcement, addresses and documents undated (Folder 3)
  - Mowles-Moulse: family reunion records (incomplete), address lists, invitations and newspaper articles undated (Folder 4)
  - Mowles-Moulse: family reunion addresses and relationship cards undated (Folder 5)
  - Mowles: address list for sending out family group sheets undated (Folder 6)
  - Mowles Album: marriage license, family group sheets, photos, wills and obituaries undated (Folder 7)
  - Moulse: Family Heritage Book undated (Folder 8)
  - Moulse: photos and notes undated (Folder 9)
  - Moulse: family group sheets and pedigree chart undated (Folder 10)
  - Moulse: family group sheets, pedigree chart, marriage license, notes and photos undated (Folder 11)
  - Moulse: family group sheets, pedigree chart, obituaries, marriage license and notes undated (Folder 12)
  - Moulse: wedding announcements, newspaper articles, funeral bill, correspondence, notes and memorial book undated (Folder 13)
  - Moulse: notes undated (Folder 14)
  - Moulse: graduation announcement, wedding announcement and invitation, obituaries, notes and newspaper article various dates (Folder 15)
  - Moulse: obituaries, memorial booklet and newspaper article various dates (Folder 16)
  - Moulse: memorial booklets, obituaries and notes various dates (Folder 17)
  - Moulse: notes, marriage announcement, photo and correspondence various dates (Folder 18)
  - Moulse: memorial booklet, notes, correspondence, photos, newspaper articles and death records various dates (Folder 19)
  - Moulse: obituary, memorial booklet, notes, photos and correspondence various dates (Folder 20)
  - Moulse: notes undated (Folder 21)
  - Moulse: magazine article on Larry Moulse and B.C. Moulse undated (Folder 22)
  - Moulse, G.H. and H.H.: personal correspondence, photos, newspaper articles, graduation announcement, wedding invitation, notes and Phi Sigma Alpha information various dates (Folder 23)
  - Moulse, G.H. and H.H.: birth certificate and marriage license various dates (Folder 24)
  - Moulse, G.H. and Huff: family group sheet, marriage records and anniversary announcement various dates (Folder 25)
  - Moulse, G.H.: issue of Norfolk and Western magazine 1959 (Folder 26)
  - Moulse, G.H.: biography summary undated (Folder 27)
  - Moulse, G.H.: interview transcript 1985 (Folder 28)
  - Moulse, G.H.: birth certificate, playhouse certificate and memorial booklet with obitiuary various dates (Folder 29)
  - Moulse, Helen H.: family tree, pedigree chart, family group sheet and D.A.R. application various dates (Folder 30)
  - Moulse, Helen H.: D.A.R. application with supporting documents various dates (Folder 31)
  - Moulse, Helen H.: D.A.R. membership and membership application various dates (Folder 32)
  - Moulse, Helen H.: personal correspondence and wedding invitation various dates (Folder 33)
  - Moulse, Helen H.: obituaries and memorial booklet various dates (Folder 34)
  - Moulse, Helen H.: genealogy and personal correspondence various dates (Folder 35)
  - Moulse, Helen H.: funeral book undated (Folder 36)
  - Moulse, E.W.: memorial service record book, church bulletin and obituary various dates (Folder 37)
  - Moulse, Elizabeth: estate settlement documents various dates (Folder 38)
  - Moulse, C.C. and E.: obituary, notes and photos various dates (Folder 39)
  - Moulse, C.M.: documents various dates (Folder 40)
  - Moulse, M.G.: documents and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 41)
  - Moulse, S.W. and Clark: family group sheets undated (Folder 42)
  - Moulse, W.D. and Wertz: family group sheets, personal correspondence and wedding invitation various dates (Folder 43)
  - Moulse, H.A. and Reitzel: pedigree chart and family group sheet undated (Folder 44)
  - Moulse, R.M.: Heller and Masoncupp - family group sheets and photos undated (Folder 45)
  - Mouls, Moul, Mowles, Moulse: marriage license, obituary, newspaper articles and notes various dates (Folder 46)
  - Mowles, Mowls, Moulds: pedigree chart, family group sheets and documents various dates (Folder 47)
  - Mouls, Mowles, Moulse: Notes undated (Folder 48)
  - Mould, Maul, Mowles, Moulse: family group sheets, obituary, marriage license, notes, pedigree chart and correspondence various dates (Folder 49)
  - Mowles, Moulse: pedigree chart and marriage license various dates (Folder 50)
  - Mowles, Moulse: family group sheets, notes, brochures and correspondence various dates (Folder 51)
  - Mowles, Moulse: copies of photos of James Mowles and G.P. Moulse and families undated (Folder 52)
  - Mowles: pedigree chart, family group sheets, marriage records and family reunion information various dates (Folder 53)
  - Mowles: memorial booklet, personal correspondence and notes various dates (Folder 54)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, memorial booklets, obituaries, photos and notes various dates (Folder 55)
- (Box 2)
  - Mowles: photos of individuals and aerial photo of farm undated (Folder 1)
  - Mowles: correspondence and copies of photos undated (Folder 2)
  - Mowles: correspondence, notes and obituaries various dates (Folder 3)
  - Mowles: correspondence, notes and photos various dates (Folder 4)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, correspondence and notes various dates (Folder 5)
  - Mowles: notes, pedigree charts, family group sheets, census and maps various dates (Folder 6)
  - Mowles: pedigree charts, family group sheets, correspondence, notes and memorial booklet various dates (Folder 7)
  - Mowles: "Family Heritage Book", contains addresses undated (Folder 8)
  - Mowles: pedigree charts and notes undated (Folder 9)
  - Mowles: correspondence, obituaries, photos and marriage announcements various dates (Folder 10)
  - Mowles: obituaries and memorial booklets various dates (Folder 11)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, marriage license and notes various dates (Folder 12)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, marriage license, marriage announcements, notes and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 13)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, correspondence and notes various dates (Folder 14)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, notes, pedigree charts and documents (Folder 15)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, marriage records and notes various dates (Folder 16)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, pedigree chart, notes and death certificate various dates (Folder 17)
  - Mowles, Cynthia M.: family group sheet, marriage licenses, pedigree chart and notes various dates (Folder 18)
  - Mowles, C.G. and Graham: family group sheets undated (Folder 19)
  - Mowles, G.W. and Kelly: family group sheets and notes undated (Folder 20)
  - Mowles, J.W. and Aliff: marriage documents, photos and family group sheets various dates (Folder 21)
  - Mowles, G.P. and Moulse: family group sheets, death records and notes various dates (Folder 22)
  - Mowles, Henry: family group sheets undated (Folder 23)
  - Mowles, J.H. and Jobe: family group sheet, marriage license and notes various dates (Folder 24)
  - Mowles: family group sheets and wedding invitation various dates (Folder 25)
  - Mowles: family group sheet undated (Folder 26)
  - Mowles: family group sheets and notes undated (Folder 27)
  - Mowles-Deaton: family group sheet, memorial booklet, obituary and notes various dates (Folder 28)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, memorial booklets, obituaries, notes, marriage announcements and pedigree chart various dates (Folder 29)
  - Mowles: family group sheets, obituaries and notes various dates (Folder 30)
  - Mowles-Minnix: family group sheets, notes and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 31)
  - Mowles, O.P.: family group sheet, obituary and notes various dates (Folder 32)
  - Mowles and Kessler: pedigree chart, family group sheet and notes various dates (Folder 33)
  - Mowles: family group sheets and wedding announcement various dates (Folder 34)
  - Mowles-Wertz: family group sheets, notes, memorial booklets and obituaries various dates (Folder 35)
  - Mowles: family group sheet, pedigree chart, obituary and memorial booklet various dates (Folder 36)
  - Mowles: Spring Park Deed 1940 (Folder 37)
  - Mowles: Spring Park homeplace cemetery - sketch, notes and photo undated (Folder 38)
  - Mowles: Spring Park newspaper article unknown date (Folder 39)
  - Mowles-Adams: family group sheet, marriage license, notes, copies of photos, heraldry and obituary various dates (Folder 40)
  - Mowles-Adams: pedigree chart, coat of arms, copies of photos and family group sheet undated (Folder 41)
  - Adams-Moulse: family group sheet and memorial booklet various dates (Folder 42)
  - Adams: correspondence with R.E. King various dates (Folder 43)
  - Moulse-Adams: pedigree chart, family group sheets and funeral records various dates (Folder 44)
  - Irby-Adams: marriage records, family group sheets and cemetery photos various dates (Folder 45)
  - Adams: family group sheet, wedding invitation, newspaper articles, notes, marriage license, funeral records and marriage announcement various dates (Folder 46)
  - Argabright-Adams: family group sheets, notes, memorial booklet, marriage and funeral records various dates (Folder 47)
  - Adams: pedigree chart, family group sheets, cemetery records and notes various dates (Folder 48)
  - Harlow-Adams: family group sheet, wedding announcement, funeral records and notes various dates (Folder 49)
  - Adams: notes and addresses undated (Folder 50)
  - Adams: family lineage narrative and notes undated (Folder 51)
  - Adams: notebook of addresses and notes undated (Folder 52)
  - Adams: notes, correspondence, family group sheets and book excerpts various dates (Folder 53)
  - Mowles-Aliff: copies of photos of J.H. Mowles, Susan Aliff and children undated (Folder 54)
  - Mowles-Aliff: family group sheet, marriage license and copies of photos various dates (Folder 55)
  - Mowls-Mowles-Aliff-Kelley: family group sheets, notes, marriage license, obituaries and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 56)
  - Moulse-Clark-Stiff: obituary, memorial booklet, notes and correspondence various dates (Folder 57)
  - Mowles-Gardner-Felty: marriage license, wedding program, family group sheets and notes various dates (Folder 58)
  - Felty-Moulse: obituary, memorial booklet and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 59)
  - Mowles-Felty: pedigree chart, family group sheets and obituary various dates (Folder 60)
  - Felty: Resolution of Thanks from church, correspondence various dates (Folder 61)
  - Kilmore-Moul: family group sheets, marriage records and notes various dates (Folder 62)
  - Kropff-Mowles: family group sheet, pedigree charts, notes, marriage licenses, newspaper articles and book excerpts various dates (Folder 63)
  - Stief-Steves-Kropff: notes and marriage license various dates (Folder 64)
  - Lawrence-Moulse: newspaper articles, memorial booklets and notes various dates (Folder 65)
  - Masoncupp-Moulse: memorial booklets, notes and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 66)
  - Moulse-Mattox: family group sheets undated (Folder 67)
  - Mattox: pedigree chart, family group sheets and notes undated (Folder 68)
  - Mattox: correspondence and notes various dates (Folder 69)
  - Mattox: family group sheets and pedigree charts undated (Folder 70)
  - Moulse-Mattox: family group sheets, marriage announcement and photos various dates (Folder 71)
  - Mattox: wedding announcement, correspondence, birth announcement and photos various dates (Folder 72)
  - Mattox-Mowles-Huff-Simmons: marriage bonds, notes and family group sheets various dates (Folder 73)
  - Mattox-Dyer: memorial booklets, obituaries, notes and wedding invitation various dates (Folder 74)
  - Biggs-Dyer: correspondence, family group sheets and list of addresses various dates (Folder 75)
  - Biggs, Walter: headstone photo and photos of cemetery undated (Folder 76)
  - Parrish-Robertson-Mowles: family group sheets, memorial booklets, obituaries, book excerpts and photoa various dates (Folder 77)
  - Robertson-Kelly-Mowls: marriage license, marriage records, family group sheets, notes, death certificates and correspondence various dates (Folder 78)
  - Robertson: correspondence, family history notes, obituaries and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 79)
  - Mowles, W.B. and Shartzer: family group sheets and marriage license various dates (Folder 80)
  - Mowles-Shartzer: family group sheets and marriage license various dates (Folder 81)
  - Mowles-Moulse-Huff: photos, obituaries, notes, memorial booklets and recipe various dates (Folder 82)
  - Moulse-Huff: Montgomery County Census, tax list and notes various dates (Folder 83)
  - Mowles-Huff: notes undated (Folder 84)
  - Mowles-Huff-Cannaday-Neighbors: notes undated (Folder 85)
  - Mowles-Huff-Cannaday: marriage records various dates (Folder 86)
  - Mowls-Mowles-Huff-Richardson: family group sheets, newspaper notices, correspondence and pedigree chart various dates (Folder 87)
  - Mowles-Huff-Terry: notes undated (Folder 88)
  - Mowles-Austen-Horne: notes undated (Folder 89)
  - Mowles-Early-Huff: marriage records various dates (Folder 90)
  - Huff-Mowles: Augusta County notes undated (Folder 91)
  - Huff-Moul: excerpts and notes from DAR Patriot Index undated (Folder 92)
  - Huff-Cannaday-Mowles: marriage records in Virginia counties various dates (Folder 93)
- (Box 3)
  - Huff-Mowles: research notes, obituaries, marriage record notes various dates (Folder 1)
  - Huff-Moulse: pedigree chart, family group sheets, notes, narrative on Huff Family and birth certificate various dates (Folder 2)
  - Huff-Moulse: obituary, memorial booklets, family group sheets and notes various dates (Folder 3)
  - Huff: family group sheets, notes, correspondence and photos various dates (Folder 4)
  - Huff: correspondence, family group sheets and notes various dates (Folder 5)
  - Huff: notes and photos undated (Folder 6)
  - Huff: family group sheets, military service records, death certificate, census notes and headstone photos various dates (Folder 7)
  - Huff: marriage licenses and copies of contracts various dates (Folder 8)
  - Huff: obituaries and notes various dates (Folder 9)
  - Huff: family group sheets, ancestral files and notes undated (Folder 10)
  - Huff: family group sheets undated (Folder 11)
  - Huff, G.: copies of Sons of the American Revolution application with supporting documents and photos (Folder 12)
  - Huff: newspaper articles and obituaries (Folder 13)
  - Huff: notes, newspaper articles, obituaries and marriage certificate various dates (Folder 14)
  - Huff: family group sheets, notes, death certificate, marriage record, and Odd Fellows records various dates (Folder 15)
  - Huff: family group sheets, death certificate, military service records and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 16)
  - Huff: military service records, newspaper articles and membership records various dates (Folder 17)
  - Huff: family group sheets, notes, obituaries, photos, SAR membership application, memorial booklets and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 18)
  - Huff: obituaries, memorial booklets, marriage announcements and death records various dates (Folder 19)
  - Huff: family group sheets, correspondence and notes various dates (Folder 20)
  - Huff: pedigree chart, correspondence and notes various dates (Folder 21)
  - Huff: notes undated (Folder 22)
  - Huff: correspondence, obituaries and notes various dates (Folder 23)
  - Huff: marriage and death certificates, notes, photos and correspondence various dates (Folder 24)
  - Huff: obituaries, biography, family group sheets and notes various dates (Folder 25)
  - Huff: family group sheets, notes, ancestral files and cemetery records various dates (Folder 26)
  - Huff: correspondence vaarious dates (Folder 27)
  - Huff: photos of cemeteries and churches in Floyd County, Virginia undated (Folder 28)
  - Huff: correspondence, family group sheets, negatives and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 29)
  - Huff: correspondence, biographical sketches and notes various dates (Folder 30)
  - Huff: correspondence, obituaries, memorial booklets, notes and photo various dates (Folder 31)
  - Huff: family group sheets, obituaries, marriage licenses and Academy Street School various dates (Folder 32)
  - Huff: family group sheets and correspondence various dates (Folder 33)
  - Huff: obituaries, notes, pedigree chart and newspaper articles various dates (Folder 34)
  - Huff: family history records compiled by Atwood J. Huff, II, family group sheets, newspaper articles and notes various dates (Folder 35)
  - Huff: excerpt from "History of Roanoke County" and notes undated (Folder 36)
  - Huff: photos, notes, obituaries and booklets various dates (Folder 37)
  - Huff: family group sheets, notes, correspondence, obituaries and pedigree charts various dates (Folder 38)
  - Huff: marriage records and family group sheets various dates (Folder 39)
  - Huff: excerpt from book on war, correspondence various dates (Folder 40)
  - Huff: pedigree chart, family group sheets and notes undated (Folder 41)
  - Huff: book excerpts, newspaper articles, obituaries and notes various dates (Folder 42)
  - Huff: family group sheets, wills and notes various dates (Folder 43)
  - Huff: pedigree chart, family group sheets, notes, book excerpts and obituaries various dates (Folder 44)
  - Huff: notes undated (Folder 45)
  - Huff: various census notes undated (Folder 46)
  - Huff: land grants and deeds from various counties various dates (Folder 47)
  - Huff: notes undated (Folder 48)
  - Huff: history and formation of Virginia counties undated (Folder 49)
  - Huff: soldiers in Revolutionary and Civil Wars various dates (Folder 50)
  - Huff: immigrants to Virginia various dates (Folder 51)
  - Huff: Huff-Hough-Moulse-Claur-Lawrence: wills in Virginia various dates (Folder 52)
  - Huff: notes undated (Folder 53)
  - Huff: Floyd County notes undated (Folder 54)
  - Huff: notes undated (Folder 55)
  - Huff: copies of personal correspondence, notes, photos, memorial booklets and documents various dates (Folder 56)
  - Huff: marriage records various dates (Folder 57)
  - Huff: notes and copies from record books various dates (Folder 58)
  - Huff: correspondence with M.E. Ferrell and pedigree charts various dates (Folder 59)
  - Huff: excerpts from Carroll County books listing Huff Family members undated (Folder 60)
  - Huff: pedigree charts, notes, correspondence, obituaries and memorial booklets various dates (Folder 61)
  - Huff: correspondence, notes and documents various dates (Folder 62)
  - Huff: marriage and anniversary records, obitiuaries, notes and membership cards various dates (Folder 63)
  - Huff: notebook containing religious questions, addresses and history of Roanoke County undated (Folder 64)
  - Huff, P.: pedigree chart, will, marriage record, notes various dates (Folder 65)
  - Huff, P.: pedirgee chart, family group sheet, will book excerpts and notes various dates (Folder 66)
  - Huff, P.: pedigree chart, will and marriage record notes various dates (Folder 67)
  - Huff, E.D.: family group sheets undated (Folder 68)
  - Huff, M.M.: family group sheets and ntoes undated (Folder 69)
  - Huff, J. and E.M.: notes, family group sheets and ancestral file undated (Folder 70)
- (Box 4)
  - Huff, I.M.: family group sheets, obituaries, notes, memorial booklets, photos and wedding program various dates (Folder 1)